I could never have imagined
لم أتخيل قط،
that a 19-year-old suicide bomber
أن مفجر إنتحاري بعمر 19 سنة،
would actually teach me a valuable lesson.
قد يعلمني درساً قيماُ.
But he did.
ولكنه فعل.
He taught me to never presume anything
علمني أن لا أضع احكاماً مسبقة
about anyone you don't know.
عن أي أحد لا أعرفه.
On a Thursday morning in July 2005,
في صباح يوم الخميس في حزيران 2005،
the bomber and I, unknowingly,
أنا والمفجّر، بدون علم،
boarded the same train carriage at the same time,
ركبنا القطار نفسه و في الوقت نفسه،
standing, apparently, just feet apart.
جالسين على مايبدو على بعد قدم واحد.
I didn't see him.
لم أره.
Actually, I didn't see anyone.
في الحيقة، لم أرَ أحداً.
You know not to look at anyone on the Tube,
كما تعلم لا أحد ينظر الى الآخر في القطار،
but I guess he saw me.
ولكنني أعتقد بأنه رآني.
I guess he looked at all of us,
أعتقد بأنه نظر الى كل واحدٍ منا،
as his hand hovered over the detonation switch.
في الوقت الذي ضغط فيه مفتاح التفجير.
I've often wondered: What was he thinking?
ولطالما تساءلت: بما كان يفكر؟
Especially in those final seconds.
خصوصاً في تلك اللحظات الأخيرة
I know it wasn't personal.
أعلم أنها لم تكن اسباباً شخصية،
He didn't set out to kill or maim me, Gill Hicks.
هو لم يأتِ الى هنا ليقتلني أو يشوهني أنا، غيل هيكس.
I mean -- he didn't know me.
أعني، هو لايعرفني.
No.
لا.
Instead, he gave me
وعلى النقيض هو أعطاني،
an unwarranted and an unwanted label.
تسمية غير مرغوبة و غير مبررة.
I had become the enemy.
أصبحت أنا العدو.
To him, I was the "other,"
بالنسبة له أنا كنت "الآخرين"
the "them," as opposed to "us."
"هم" التي تعود لنا "نحن"
The label "enemy" allowed him to dehumanize us.
تلك التسمية "العدو" سمحت له بأن يجردنا من إنسانيتنا،
It allowed him to push that button.
سمَحت له بالضغط على الزر.
And he wasn't selective.
ولم يكن إختيارياَ،
Twenty-six precious lives were taken in my carriage alone,
ست وعشرين حياة غالية لفظت أنفاسها، فقط على متن عربتي.
and I was almost one of them.
وكنت على وشك أن أكون إحداها،
In the time it takes to draw a breath,
وفي غمضة عين،
we were plunged into a darkness so immense
غرقنا جميعنا في ظلام حالك،
that it was almost tangible;
وقد كان محسوساً،
what I imagine wading through tar might be like.
ماتخيلته عن شكل الخوض داخل القطران.
We didn't know we were the enemy.
لم نكن نعلم بأننا نحن العدو،
We were just a bunch of commuters who, minutes earlier,
كنا مجرد حفنة من الركاب الذين لتوهم،
had followed the Tube etiquette:
أتبعوا آداب النفق،
no direct eye contact,
لا أتصال عين مباشر
no talking
لا حديث
and absolutely no conversation.
وبالتأكيد لا محادثات.
But in the lifting of the darkness,
ولكن ما أن انقشع الظلام،
we were reaching out.
حتى أصبحنا نمد أيدينا لبعضنا.
We were helping each other.
كنا نساعد بعض البعض،
We were calling out our names,
وكنا نصرخ باسماءنا،
a little bit like a roll call,
وكأننا قليلاً في عملية تصويت،
waiting for responses.
بأنتظار الرد.
"I'm Gill. I'm here.
"انا غيل، أنا هنا
I'm alive.
لا أزال حية،
OK."
حسناً"
"I'm Gill.
"أنا غيل،
Here.
هنا
Alive.
لا أزال حية
OK."
حسناً"
I didn't know Alison.
لم أكن أعرف أليسون،
But I listened for her check-ins every few minutes.
ولكنني سمعت لما تم التأكد من دخولها قبل بضع دقائق،
I didn't know Richard.
لم أكن اعرف ريتشارد،
But it mattered to me that he survived.
ولكنه أفرحني خبر نجاته.
All I shared with them
كل ماشاركته معهم،
was my first name.
كان أسمي الأول،
They didn't know
لم يكونوا يعرفوا،
that I was a head of a department at the Design Council.
انني كنت رئيسة قسم مجلس التصميم،
And here is my beloved briefcase,
وهاهي حقيبتي الحبيبة،
also rescued from that morning.
أيضاً تم العثور عليها ذاك اليوم.
They didn't know that I published architecture and design journals,
لم يكونوا يعرفوا بأنني قد نشرت مذكرات العمارة والتصميم،
that I was a Fellow of the Royal Society of Arts,
وأنني كنت عضوة في الجمعية الملكية للفنون،
that I wore black --
بأنني ارتدي الاسود،
still do --
لا أزال.
that I smoked cigarillos.
وأنني أدخن السيقارلوس،
I don't smoke cigarillos anymore.
أقلعت عن تدخينها.
I drank gin and I watched TED Talks,
وأنني كنت اشرب الزنجبيل وأشاهد TED مؤتمرات،
of course, never dreaming that one day I would be standing,
وبالطبع لم أكن أحلم أن اقف هنا يوماً،
balancing on prosthetic legs,
متوازنة على أرجلي الصناعية،
giving a talk.
أقدم عرضاُ.
I was a young Australian woman doing extraordinary things in London.
كنت شابة أسترالية يافعة أقدم أعمالي الاستثنائية في لندن،
And I wasn't ready for that all to end.
ولم أكن مستعدة لاعتبر ان تلك هي النهاية،
I was so determined to survive
كنت مصممةً على العيش،
that I used my scarf to tie tourniquets around the tops of my legs,
لدرجة أني استخدمت وشاحي بربطه على اعلى ساقيّ حتى أوقف النزيف.
and I just shut everything and everyone out,
وتجاهلت على كل شيئ أخر وكل شخص آخر،
to focus, to listen to myself,
من أجل ان اركز ان أستمع لنفسي،
to be guided by instinct alone.
من أجل تقودني الفطرة لوحدها،
I lowered my breathing rate.
أخفضت مستوى تنفسي،
I elevated my thighs.
ورفعت فخذاي،
I held myself upright
أمسكت بنفسي بشكل مستقيم.
and I fought the urge to close my eyes.
وقاومت الرغبة بغلق عيناي،
I held on for almost an hour,
تماسكت تقريباً لمدة ساعة،
an hour to contemplate the whole of my life
ساعة أمضيتها في التفكّر بحياتي.
up until this point.
الى تلك النقطة،
Perhaps I should have done more.
لربما كان بأمكاني فعل أكثر من هذا،
Perhaps I could have lived more, seen more.
لربما كان بأمكاني العيش أكثر،أن ارى أكثر.
Maybe I should have gone running, dancing, taken up yoga.
لربما كان بأمكاني الذهاب للجري، الرقص وممارسة اليوغا،
But my priority and my focus was always my work.
ولكن أأولوياتي وتركيزي منصبتان دائماً على العمل،
I lived to work.
عشت من أجل العمل.
Who I was on my business card
من أكون على بطاقة العمل،
mattered to me.
لطالما أهمني السؤال.
But it didn't matter down in that tunnel.
ولكنه لم يكن مهماً في اسفل ذلك النفق،
By the time I felt that first touch
في الوقت الذي شعرت فيه بأول لمسة،
from one of my rescuers,
من أحد فريق الانقاذ،
I was unable to speak,
لم أكن قادرة على التكلم،
unable to say even a small word, like "Gill."
لم أكن قادرة على نطق كلمة صغيرة، مثل "غيل"
I surrendered my body to them.
أسلمت جسدي لهم،
I had done all I possibly could,
وكنت قد فعلت مابوسعي،
and now I was in their hands.
والآن أنا بين أيديهم.
I understood
فهمت.
just who and what humanity really is,
ماهو وماهية الانسانية،
when I first saw the ID tag
للوهلة الاولى التي رأيت فيها البطاقة،
that was given to me when I was admitted to hospital.
التي اُعطيت لي عندما وصلت للمستشفى.
And it read:
كُتب عليها :
"One unknown estimated female."
"أمراة مجهولة مُقدّرة"
One unknown estimated female.
أمراة مجهولة مُقدّرة
Those four words were my gift.
هذه الكلمات الأربع كانت هديتي،
What they told me very clearly
ما أخبروني به بكل وضوح،
was that my life was saved,
انه تمّ إنقاذي،
purely because I was a human being.
فقط لأنني أنسان،
Difference of any kind made no difference
و ايّ اختلافات من نوع آخر لم يُلتفت إالبها.
to the extraordinary lengths that the rescuers were prepared to go
كل تلك المسافة الطويلة التي كان رجال الانقاذ يستعد لقطعها،
to save my life,
من أجل إنقاذي ،
to save as many unknowns as they could,
من أجل انقاذ ماستطاعوا.
and putting their own lives at risk.
وتعريض أنفسهم للخطر،
To them, it didn't matter if I was rich or poor,
بالنسبة لهم، ليس مهماً،
the color of my skin,
لون بشرتي،
whether I was male or female,
ما إذا كنت رجلاً او أمرأة،
my sexual orientation,
ميولي الجنسية،
who I voted for,
ولمن صوّت،
whether I was educated,
سواءاّ كنت متعلمة،
if I had a faith or no faith at all.
لو كنت مؤمنة أم ملحدة،
Nothing mattered
لاشيئ من هذا يهم.
other than I was a precious human life.
عدا أنني حياة أنسان مقدرة.
I see myself as a living fact.
أرى نفسي كإثبات حياة،
I am proof
انا دليل،
that unconditional love and respect can not only save,
الحب غير المشروط والاحترام ليس بأمكانه فقط أنقاذ حياة
but it can transform lives.
ولكن بأمكانه تغيير حياة
Here is a wonderful image of one of my rescuers, Andy, and I
هنا صورة مذهلة لأحد فريق الانقاذ انا واندي
taken just last year.
التقطناها السنة الفائتة
Ten years after the event,
عشر سنوات مابعد الحادثة
and here we are, arm in arm.
وها نحن الآن يداً بيد
Throughout all the chaos,
من داخل كل هذة الفوضى
my hand was held tightly.
اُمسكت يداي بقوة
My face was stroked gently.
ولُمس وجهي برفق
What did I feel?
بما شعرت ؟
I felt loved.
شعرت بأنني محبوبة
What's shielded me from hatred and wanting retribution,
ما حماني من الكارهين وممن يريدون الانتقام
what's given me the courage to say:
ما أعطاني القوة لأن اقول
this ends with me
هذا انتهى بي الى
is love.
الحب
I was loved.
لقد كنت محبوبة
I believe the potential for widespread positive change
اؤمن بأن امكانية نشر تغيير ايجابي على نطاق واسع
is absolutely enormous
بالتأكيد ضخمة
because I know what we're capable of.
لأنني اعلم بما انت قادر عليه
I know the brilliance of humanity.
اعلم مقدار الذكاء في الانسان
So this leaves me with some pretty big things to ponder
وهذا يتركتي بالعديد من الامور للتساؤل
and some questions for us all to consider:
وبعض الاسئلة التي علينا جميعنا أعتبارها
Is what unites us not far greater than what can ever divide?
أليس مايوحدنا أكبر بكثير مما يقسمنا
Does it have to take a tragedy or a disaster
هل يجب ان تحدث لنا مأسآة او كارثة حتى
for us to feel deeply connected as one species,
حتى نشعر بعمق الاتصال الذي بيننا كفصيلة
as human beings?
كبشر ؟
And when will we embrace the wisdom of our era
متى سنبرز حكمة عصرنا
to rise above mere tolerance
وأن نسمو الى التسامح
and move to an acceptance
وأن نقبلَ
for all who are only a label until we know them?
كل من وضعناه تحت تسمية الى أن نعرفه جيداً
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)